<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://obis.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://obis.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-11T12:27:02+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ocean Biodiversity Information System (OBIS)</title><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">IODC-III, call for abstracts - Join forces with OBIS to showcase the importance of fit-for-purpose and actionable data for ocean biodiversity</title><link href="https://obis.org/2025/01/03/IODC3-call-for-abstracts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IODC-III, call for abstracts - Join forces with OBIS to showcase the importance of fit-for-purpose and actionable data for ocean biodiversity" /><published>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2025/01/03/IODC3-call-for-abstracts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2025/01/03/IODC3-call-for-abstracts.html"><![CDATA[<p>Organized by the International Oceanographic Data and Information Exchange (IODE)—a programme of UNESCO’s Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission—the International Ocean Data Conference (IODC) is the not-to-be-missed meeting point for the global ocean data community. The conference is an active collaboration platform that drives progress on critical marine data-related issues and facilitates connections between scientists and decision-makers. The third edition of the IODC (IODC-III) will take place on March 10–11, 2025, online and in Santa Marta, Colombia, under the theme “The Data We Need for the Ocean We Want”, focusing on marine data actionability and developing capacity in ocean science through improved data-, information-, and knowledge-sharing.</p>

<p>Opening the IODC-III program, OBIS will host a session titled <em>“Ocean Biodiversity: How we can collectively contribute to the needs of the Convention on Biological Diversity’s Global Biodiversity Framework (GBF) and the UN Convention on the Law of the Sea’s Biodiversity Beyond National Jurisdiction (BBNJ)”,</em> chaired by Katherine Tattersall and Dan Lear, the OBIS Steering Group and Data Coordination Group Co-Chairs, with support from Ward Appeltans, OBIS Programme Manager.</p>

<p>At a time when ocean biodiversity data is at the heart of marine conservation evidence-based decision-making processes—such as environmental impact assessments, natural capital accounting, marine conservation planning, progress tracking, and marine biorisk monitoring—this session emphasizes the need for a collective, standardized, quality-driven, and holistic approach to improving the accessibility and actionability of ocean biodiversity data. The session’s organizers welcome abstracts showcasing projects and initiatives that facilitate access to accurate and fit-for-purpose marine biodiversity data at local, regional, and global levels, supporting IODE and OBIS in their mission to deliver FAIR and open data, as well as actionable products and tools. Read more about the session here: https://oceandataconference.org/iodc-iii-programme/</p>

<p><strong>Abstract submission is open until 24 January 2025 (midnight CET). Submitters will be notified of the selection committee decision by 15 February 2025 at the latest.</strong></p>

<p>You can find here the complete guidelines for the submission of an abstract: <a href="https://oceandataconference.org/call-for-abstracts-iodc3">https://oceandataconference.org/call-for-abstracts-iodc3</a></p>

<p>The complete programme of the conference is available here: <a href="https://oceandataconference.org/iodc-iii-programme">https://oceandataconference.org/iodc-iii-programme</a></p>

<p>Cover image: Emilie Boulanger / OBIS</p>]]></content><author><name>OBIS</name></author><category term="actionable data" /><category term="community" /><category term="capacity development" /><category term="IODC-III" /><category term="Policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Participate in the OBIS-led session at the third edition of the International Ocean Data Conference on 10-11 March 2025]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/IODC3-call1-thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/IODC3-call1-thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Living Data 2025 - The call for sessions is open. Submit yours today!</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/12/26/Living-data-2025-call-for-sessions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Living Data 2025 - The call for sessions is open. Submit yours today!" /><published>2024-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/12/26/Living-data-2025-call-for-sessions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/12/26/Living-data-2025-call-for-sessions.html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://e1.envoke.com/ext/click/go/8222b9820fe8006b858626ac221ed140/95b888404828d13f201676478c302134/7cfc6fcadc2ef0912972698a1fbd21e5">Living Data 2025 Conference</a>, taking place on <strong>October 21-24 in Bogotá, Colombia</strong>, will bring together four leading biodiversity networks: <a href="https://e1.envoke.com/ext/click/go/8222b9820fe8006b858626ac221ed140/812c5465297ebc72288676478c302902/7cfc6fcadc2ef0912972698a1fbd21e5">TDWG</a>, <a href="https://e1.envoke.com/ext/click/go/8222b9820fe8006b858626ac221ed140/46b81a0ac4a678b18d8676478c302fbd/7cfc6fcadc2ef0912972698a1fbd21e5">GBIF</a>, <a href="https://e1.envoke.com/ext/click/go/8222b9820fe8006b858626ac221ed140/9aa4440d963888d9e7a676478c3037af/7cfc6fcadc2ef0912972698a1fbd21e5">OBIS</a>, and GEO BON. Under the theme “United information driving transformation,” the event will explore how integrated biodiversity and geological data can address global challenges and support informed decision-making.</p>

<p>Focusing on <strong>Open Data</strong>, <strong>Data Integration</strong>, <strong>Biodiversity Data Application</strong>, and <strong>Community Engagement</strong>, the conference will highlight advancements in data standards, workflows, and technologies. Participants will engage with practical tools, analyze ecological trends, and explore ways to integrate diverse knowledge systems, including Indigenous and local expertise. Living Data 2025 aims to strengthen collaboration, build capacity, and expand equitable access to data and tools, supporting biodiversity monitoring and management.</p>

<p>Visit the website <a href="https://e1.envoke.com/ext/click/go/8222b9820fe8006b858626ac221ed140/67bda441b3118722933676478c303fdc/7cfc6fcadc2ef0912972698a1fbd21e5">livingdata2025.com</a> and sign up to its newsletter to stay updated. The call for sessions is officially open, <a href="https://e1.envoke.com/ext/click/go/8222b9820fe8006b858626ac221ed140/495ed2068cee23bc836676478c30477f/7cfc6fcadc2ef0912972698a1fbd21e5">submit yours</a> now!</p>]]></content><author><name>OBIS</name></author><category term="data" /><category term="Living Data 2025" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Participate in Living Data 2025 to increase collaboration, capacity and equitable access to data and tools supporting biodiversity monitoring and management.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/2024-12-26-Living_Data_Conference_Call_for_sessions_thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/2024-12-26-Living_Data_Conference_Call_for_sessions_thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">UNESCO eDNA Expeditions - Successfully transforming innovative eDNA sampling into actionable data with OBIS expertise</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/12/09/eDNAdashboard.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UNESCO eDNA Expeditions - Successfully transforming innovative eDNA sampling into actionable data with OBIS expertise" /><published>2024-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/12/09/eDNAdashboard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/12/09/eDNAdashboard.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Spanning 21 marine World Heritage sites in 19 countries, the UNESCO eDNA Expeditions pilot program demonstrated the transformative potential of citizen science in enhancing ocean biodiversity monitoring and conservation. OBIS, in collaboration with the World Heritage Centre, implemented cutting-edge eDNA sampling techniques and developed an advanced data dashboard for the programme, paving the way for future large-scale biodiversity monitoring campaigns.</strong></p>

<p>Environmental DNA (eDNA) is an affordable, non-invasive, reliable, and efficient biodiversity monitoring method that relies on collecting and analyzing genetic material shed by organisms in their surroundings. While the analysis of the samples involves complex molecular biology and bioinformatics techniques to identify DNA sequences, the collection of the samples is straightforward. It can be accomplished even by non-specialists, empowering citizens globally to participate in a crucial biodiversity monitoring process. Building on this potential, UNESCO launched the eDNA Expeditions programme. This 3-year initiative gave 250 schoolchildren worldwide the opportunity to participate in a unique biodiversity monitoring pilot programme at 21 marine World Heritage sites.</p>

<p>The UNESCO eDNA Expeditions’ outcome was stunning. Through 396 samples taken at the 21 sites, the volunteers contributed to identifying more than 4400 marine species, including about 86 shark and ray species, 28 marine mammal species, and 3 turtle species. Among the findings were 120 species listed as vulnerable, endangered, or critically endangered on the IUCN Red List.</p>

<p>The programme also contributed to detecting rare species, such as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commerson%27s_dolphin">Commerson’s dolphin</a> or the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giant_guitarfish">Giant Guitarfish</a>. Even more stunning was the realization that the UNESCO eDNA Expeditions programme detected 10 to 20% of the expected local fauna in sampling sites, an exceptional accomplishment for such a small campaign. Achieving the same result using traditional surveying methods could have taken years and cost several million dollars.</p>

<p>The highest number of species was recorded in New Caledonia, with 833 different species identified, including the greatest number of fish species (418 species). In contrast, the Ningaloo Coast in Australia had the highest diversity of sharks and rays (26 species) and also the greatest number of threatened species listed on the IUCN Red List (24 species, of which 4 are Critically Endangered, 6 are Endangered and 14 are classified as Vulnerable). “These numbers are truly mind-blowing, considering they were derived from filtering just a few litres of seawater”, said <strong>Ward Appeltans</strong>, head of UNESCO’s Ocean Biodiversity Information System (OBIS) and coordinator of this eDNA project together with Fanny Douvere, head of the UNESCO World Heritage marine programme. “These UNESCO sites are truly some of the planet’s most precious marine treasures,” added <strong>Fanny Douvere</strong>.</p>

<p>Even more importantly, one of the programme’s key findings was that ocean warming is pushing numerous species outside their known thermal ranges, shedding an alarming light on the need for increased, drastic conservation action in the monitored areas.<br />
The project estimated that already 16% of the detected species is currently experiencing heat stress in at least one site, and in the most likely climate scenario (SSP2) this number will double and increase to 33% and even to 52% in the worst case scenario (SSP5) by 2100. The biggest limitation of this method of estimating thermal risk is the uncertainty regarding the extent to which species can adapt to higher temperatures. This challenge is particularly acute in tropical regions, where extreme temperatures are expected, and we currently lack any analogues for meaningful comparison. “These numbers are very alarming”, says <strong>Ward Appeltans</strong>, coordinator of OBIS. “The impact of global warming in temperate areas might be less severe in terms of biodiversity, and some may even see an increase in the number of species by new warm water species coming in, but for tropical areas adding 2-3 degrees Celsius on the already warm water will be dramatic for marine life. For almost all coastal species it might simply become too hot if they have no coping mechanism”.</p>

<p><strong>OBIS contribution, from data collection to actionable integration</strong></p>

<p>A pioneering project, the UNESCO eDNA Expeditions covers the entire marine biodiversity observation data chain, from collection and analysis to integration into actionable, user-friendly dashboards. Bringing its unique, world-renowned eDNA expertise and its experience in integrating large quantities of data into usable interfaces, OBIS played a crucial role in the success of this adventure. If eDNA sampling is relatively simple, ensuring the collected samples’ usability, durability, and quality is fundamental to the method’s reliability. For the UNESCO eDNA Expeditions, OBIS eDNA experts selected  an affordable sampling kit and a robust, age-adapted scientific protocol to make the technique accessible to schoolkids and adaptable anywhere worldwide, with <a href="https://www.unesco.org/en/edna-training-materials?hub=66910">instructions</a> in Arabic, Danish, French, German, English and Spanish. The protocol consisted of measuring the sample’s environment (temperature, salinity), collecting seawater from the shore or at sea using sterile equipment, passing the collected water through a syringe into an enclosed filter to capture DNA material, adding a neutral agent for preservation, labelling the sample using a unique identification tag, recording the tag into a database using a smartphone logged into a specifically developed <a href="http://samples.ednaexpeditions.org">sample portal</a> and storing the sample until its transportation to a laboratory for analysis.</p>

<p>The UNESCO-provided sampling kit for the young collection teams was designed with usability in mind. It focused on avoiding cross-contamination, featuring easy-to-use, field- and fool-proof tools in sizes and materials adapted to the teams’ ages. “With this kit, we wanted to be sure that the kids in sampling teams would have fun, would learn, and would provide usable DNA material,” explains <strong>Saara Suominen</strong>, a leading OBIS eDNA expert and a lead-author of <em>Engaging communities to safeguard ocean life<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></em>, a UNESCO publication about the eDNA Expeditions. “We were inspired by the quality of the results. We applied a standardized biodiversity surveying method that anyone can use. This can completely change how we monitor marine biodiversity in the future, as we can collect more data, more often and even in the most remote areas of the globe.”</p>

<p>After DNA analysis of the samples in specialized laboratories, the collected data had to be treated, organized, and integrated. Sequencing of the 396 viable samples yielded over 600 million DNA sequences, and subsequent analysis using the OBIS developed <a href="https://github.com/iobis/PacMAN-pipeline">PacMAN bioinformatics pipeline</a>, identified 450,000 unique sequences. The OBIS data experts developed an in-house dedicated platform for the UNESCO eDNA Expeditions programme, with a strong focus on usability, user-friendliness, and accessibility of the data collected. The result is a series of connected, intuitive dashboards available at <a href="https://dashboard.ednaexpeditions.org/">dashboard.ednaexpeditions.org</a></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EzEAtMvvgoo?si=gYrLw6YqaZsUsBVE_" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The UNESCO eDNA Expeditions Dashboard combines user-friendly design, accessible insights, and advanced DNA-derived scientific content. “We have designed the UNESCO eDNA Expeditions Dashboard with a diverse range of users in mind,” explains <strong>Pieter Provoost</strong>, OBIS Data Manager and one of the architects behind the platform. “The Dashboard features multiple navigation interfaces tailored to better support users’ needs. We prioritized a visual and fit-for-purpose interface to avoid overwhelming non-specialists with content that was too technical. The Dashboard is built on a layered, Open Science approach that maximizes inclusivity, offering educative content for teachers or curious citizens and actionable insights aimed at marine site managers or policymakers to support evidence-based decision-making.”</p>

<p>“The UNESCO eDNA Expeditions programme is a real-life demonstration of the revolutionary efficiency of eDNA surveying techniques in marine environments,” explains Mrs <strong>Audrey Azoulay</strong>, Director General of UNESCO. “It’s a testimony of the fantastic potential of citizen engagement in biodiversity monitoring. This programme can serve as the blueprint for future scaled-up marine biodiversity monitoring campaigns, contributing to a better understanding of our Ocean and achieving the World’s objective set in 2022 by the Kunming-Montréal Global Biodiversity Framework: to protect a third of the ocean by 2030”.</p>

<p>With the UNESCO eDNA Expeditions, data is just a click away from action.</p>

<p>Read the full report here <a href="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000392159">https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000392159</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Acknowledgement</strong><br />
UNESCO eDNA expeditions 2022-2024 project was funded by the Government of Flanders (Kingdom of Belgium) through the UNESCO-Flanders Trust Funds for Science and Culture.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000392159">https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000392159</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>OBIS</name></author><category term="eDNA" /><category term="eDNA Expeditions" /><category term="UNESCO" /><category term="eDNA Dashboards" /><category term="Policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Decoding the Ocean - UNESCO eDNA Expeditions Unveil Ocean Biodiversity]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/eDNA-Dash-thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/eDNA-Dash-thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Help Build a Holistic Ocean Observing System: Survey for a Collaborative Ocean Observing Blueprint</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/11/25/bioecocean-blueprintsurvey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Help Build a Holistic Ocean Observing System: Survey for a Collaborative Ocean Observing Blueprint" /><published>2024-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/11/25/bioecocean-blueprintsurvey</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/11/25/bioecocean-blueprintsurvey.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>How do we collaborate for a better understanding of life in the ocean? How do we enable and facilitate communication at different scales and across sectors?</strong></p>

<p>The Horizon Europe project <a href="https://bioecoocean.org/">BioEcoOcean</a> is spearheading efforts to answer these questions and improve collaboration and understanding of marine life through the development of a <strong>Blueprint for Integrated Ocean Science (BIOS)</strong>, or simply referred to as “the Blueprint” (Figure 1).</p>

<p>This innovative tool will aim to guide ocean observing programs in all aspects of ocean observation, from the early planning stages to data collection and management, to their application in policy and decision making. The Blueprint is envisioned to be a co-created question-based tool that facilitates communication and collaboration across sectors through guiding questions. Read more about the Blueprint and its development <a href="https://bioecoocean.org/actions/blueprint-living-lab/">here</a>.</p>

<figure>
  <img alt="blueprint-web-figure" src="/images/bioecoocean-blueprintweb.png" width="50%" />
  <figcaption><i>Fig 1. Early graphic demonstrating the components of the Blueprint for Integrated Ocean Science. Lines connecting each component indicate interconnectivity.</i></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>These guiding questions will be designed to be broadly applicable across environments, Essential Ocean Variables, sectors, and other parties, fostering collaboration on complex issues. With <strong>co-creation</strong> at its core, BioEcoOcean invites the community to contribute through workshops, surveys, and testing.</p>

<h2 id="contribute-to-the-first-bioecoocean-survey">Contribute to the first BioEcoOcean survey</h2>

<p>The first survey, open until <strong>15 January 2025</strong>, aims to gather feedback on challenges and opportunities in connecting the suggested components in the Blueprint. It takes 8–10 minutes to complete and primarily asks participants to indicate the degree to which they agree with various statements.</p>

<p>To participate, take the survey <a href="https://doit.medfarm.uu.se/bin/kurt3/kurt/8869543">here</a>.</p>

<p>For more details or to collaborate on testing early versions, contact BioEcoOcean at bioecoocean@uu.se.</p>]]></content><author><name>OBIS secretariat</name></author><category term="BioEcoOcean" /><category term="survey" /><category term="Horizon Europe" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Horizon Europe project BioEcoOcean is seeking input via a survey for the development of a Blueprint for Integrated Ocean Science.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/blueprintsurvey-thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/blueprintsurvey-thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Marine perspectives on COP16-Reinforced global collaborations to better support conservation</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/11/24/COP16.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marine perspectives on COP16-Reinforced global collaborations to better support conservation" /><published>2024-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/11/24/COP16</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/11/24/COP16.html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2022, at COP15, Parties to the United Nations Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) adopted the Kunming-Montreal Global Biodiversity Framework (GBF), setting a path for concrete actions to protect and restore global biodiversity to a healthy state. With four overarching goals for 2050 and 23 action-oriented Targets to be achieved by 2030, the GBF showcased the Parties’ commitment to conservation efforts.</p>

<p><img style="float: left; margin-right: 20px;" />
  <img src="/images/COP16_IOC.jpeg" alt="COP16" width="600" />
&lt;/img&gt;</p>

<p>_From left to right: Alison Clausen (IOC/Ocean Decade), Vidar Helgesen (IOC executive secretary), Emma Heslop (IOC/GOOS) and Ward Appeltans (IOC/OBIS)</p>

<p>Two years later, during COP16, which took place in Cali, Colombia, from October 21 to November 1, 2024, the Parties reviewed and assessed the progress of the GBF implementation. The state of play of Ocean observations and marine conservation efforts were at the heart of the discussions, with the Parties highlighting the positive advancements and remarkable contributions of the infrastructures involved.</p>

<p><strong>OBIS and GOOS’s fundamental role in ocean and marine biodiversity observations</strong></p>

<p>The Ocean Biodiversity Information System (OBIS) and the Global Ocean Observation System (GOOS), both part of the Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission of UNESCO will be instrumental in supporting GBF Targets. The two infrastructures are operational for decades, bringing together a global network of experts, projects and regional and national structures and could immediately support the Parties in implementing and reporting on the GBF targets.</p>

<p>By providing robust, long-term, reliable and standardized FAIR global marine biodiversity data and data-driven actionable monitoring tools such as maps and dashboards, OBIS can support the Parties in assessing ongoing marine biodiversity mitigation actions and planning biosecurity, biodiversity risk reduction and conservation strategies.</p>

<p><strong>OBIS and GOOS’s Reinforced Role as Fundamental Supporters of the Global Biodiversity Framework at COP16</strong></p>

<p>At COP16, OBIS’s role in supporting the GBF was reconfirmed. OBIS is included in the framework as a complementary indicator for Goal D (“Invest and Collaborate”), Target 20 (“Strengthen Capacity-Building, Technology Transfer, and Scientific and Technical Cooperation for Biodiversity”) and Target 21 (“Ensure That Knowledge Is Available and Accessible To Guide Biodiversity Action”).</p>

<p>The Parties also adopted during the Conference the second cycle of the Ecologically or Biologically Significant Marine Areas (EBSA) process established under the Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD). During the first cycle of the EBSA process, which ran from 2011 to 2018, OBIS provided vital information on marine species distributions, habitats, and ecosystems, contributing to identifying and describing 321 EBSAs across the ocean. These areas have since informed marine spatial planning and conservation efforts at national and international levels. The EBSA second cycle aims to refine–based on evidence–existing EBSAs’ descriptions, identify new ones, and incorporate the latest advances in marine biodiversity data collection and analysis. With its ever-growing database on marine biodiversity and the continuous development of advanced monitoring tools and techniques such as eDNA, OBIS is poised to maintain its critical role in the second EBSA process, ensuring that EBSAs’ identification remains transparent, evidence-based, and fit for purpose.</p>

<p>During the Conference, UNESCO-IOC’s three systems–OBIS, GOOS and ODIS, the Ocean Data and Information System–were recognized by the CBD’s Subsidiary Body on Scientific, Technical and Technological Advice (SBSTTA) as the operational and ready ocean components of the upcoming Global Biodiversity Observing System (GBIOS). This proposed, not yet fully operational initiative has been developed by the Group on Earth Observations Biodiversity Observation Network (GEO BON) and its partners to provide the critical data needed to monitor biodiversity change and target action. GBIOS is a collaboration-based effort relying on existing networks, similar to the global weather network.</p>

<p>“The recognition by the Parties of OBIS, GOOS and ODIS’s excellent contributions to ocean biodiversity observation and marine conservation crowns decades of collaborative efforts from our community in providing robust, FAIR and trustable data,” says Ward Appeltans, OBIS Programme Manager. “Global scientific collaboration is vital to address the urgent challenges of biodiversity loss. Together, as scientists, we need to strengthen our efforts to ensure a sustainable future for our Ocean.”</p>

<p>By recognizing the critical roles of OBIS, GOOS, and ODIS in advancing global biodiversity goals, COP16 marked a turning point for ocean observations and marine conservation efforts. The operational preparedness of the IOC and the quality of the data it provides confirm our capacity to play an important part on the global stage in tackling biodiversity loss and making the ocean a healthy reservoir of life.</p>

<div class="post-quote">
”The recognition by the Parties of OBIS, GOOS, and ODIS’s excellent contributions to ocean biodiversity observation and marine conservation crowns decades of collaborative efforts from our community to provide robust, FAIR, and trustable data. Global scientific collaboration is vital to address the urgent challenges of biodiversity loss. Together, as scientists, we need to strengthen our efforts to ensure a sustainable future for our Ocean.”
  <div class="post-quote-author">Ward Appeltans, OBIS Programme Manager</div>
</div>

<p><strong>Did you miss the OBIS, GOOS and IOC-related streams at COP16? No worries, we have you covered here!</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/xUUwmvwXVn0?t=16115s">Overview of IOC tools and GOOS</a>, featuring Emma Heslop (IOC)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/xUUwmvwXVn0?t=17517s">OBIS-GBIF collaboration</a>, featuring Kyle Copas (GBIF)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/xUUwmvwXVn0?t=18937s">OBIS and how it can contribute to the CBD GBF</a>, featuring Ward Appeltans (IOC)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>OBIS</name></author><category term="COP16" /><category term="Global Ocean Observing System (GOOS)" /><category term="Ocean Data and Information System (ODIS)" /><category term="Global Biodiversity Framework (GBF)" /><category term="Ocean Observations" /><category term="Marine Conservation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With a dedicated Ocean Day and numerous positive concrete outcomes for ocean observations and marine biodiversity conservation, COP16 was a milestone for advancing global ocean observing and information systems. The formal recognition of OBIS and GOOS as crucial marine components of the Global Biodiversity Framework demonstrates the readiness of the two infrastructures to accelerate marine knowledge provision to better protect our Ocean.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/COP16-thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/COP16-thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Shaping the Future of Marine Biodiversity Data - Takeaways from the 6th OBIS Executive Committee Meeting</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/11/22/obis-ec6-report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shaping the Future of Marine Biodiversity Data - Takeaways from the 6th OBIS Executive Committee Meeting" /><published>2024-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/11/22/obis-ec6-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/11/22/obis-ec6-report.html"><![CDATA[<p>You can access the detailed report of the meeting at <a href="https://oceanexpert.org/document/35296">https://oceanexpert.org/document/35296</a></p>

<p><strong>Improving coordination within the community</strong></p>

<p>OBIS is a global community of 34 Regional and Thematic Nodes representing over 1,000 institutions and over 6,000 scientists and data managers from 99 countries. Collectively, they deliver 1+ million new marine biodiversity records per month. Coordination between these contributors is essential for OBIS to efficiently treat, aggregate, organize, and make such data actionable and accessible. To that end, the OBIS Executive Committee introduced three topic-centred coordination groups: the <strong>Product Coordination Group</strong> (PCG) focuses on developing high-quality, trustable, science-based, actionable, robust and user-friendly data products, such as biodiversity indicators and maps; the <strong>Data Coordination Group</strong> (DCG) ensures the quality and FAIRness of OBIS data through quality-control processes and alignment with global standards, supporting Nodes in data publishing, and addressing technical challenges in data management; and the <strong>Nodes Coordination Group</strong> (NCG), in charge of strengthening collaboration and capacity across the OBIS Nodes network through training, mentoring, and regular engagement to ensure optimal contributions. The coordination groups will meet regularly and constantly dialogue with the OBIS community. The groups will set up tools and channels, such as forums and wikis, to facilitate exchanges between contributors, tackle issues collectively and improve support.</p>

<p><strong>Strengthening the OBIS brand to enhance communication and outreach</strong></p>

<p>The 6th Executive Committee meeting participants highlighted the importance of reinforcing OBIS as a brand to support its recognition as a global leader and a driving force in marine biodiversity data. OBIS is a robust, independent, and trustworthy data source, and its scientific contributions and societal impact could be better showcased. The participants drafted four development paths: strengthening OBIS’s perception through coherent and unified actions, improving the OBIS website interface to fit different users better and match current design standards, producing impactful OBIS storylines to highlight its commitment to scientific excellence and real-life impact in marine science and conservation, crafting a set of key strategic messages to enforce OBIS position as a leading global scientific infrastructure. These development paths will be coordinated, expanded, and integrated into a broader, longer-term brand and communication strategy.</p>

<p><strong>A strategic vision for the future</strong></p>

<p>OBIS is preparing for significant events in 2025, including the 3rd International Ocean Data Conference (IODC-3) on 10-11 March, the 28th IODE Committee meeting on 12-14 March, the One Ocean Science Congress on 4-6 June, and the Living Data 2025 conference—a collaborative effort with other global biodiversity networks such as GEO BON, TDWG, and GBIF, 21-24 October. These events are crucial opportunities for facilitating strategic partnerships and advancing global biodiversity observation initiatives. They are also a unique occasion for OBIS to increase its visibility, reinforce its legitimacy, and advocate for the critical importance of marine biodiversity data.<br />
As the demand for high-quality, trustable, and independent marine biodiversity data continues to rise, OBIS is uniquely positioned to provide data and services to a growing range of users and foster synergies with other IODE activities. The OBIS Executive Committee developed a comprehensive work plan to sustain OBIS’s progress, addressing both short-term and long-term strategic goals, such as enhancing the interoperability of its data and strengthening its role within global biodiversity frameworks. The committee also stressed the need for OBIS to balance visionary ambitions with practical resource planning to meet its users’ ever-growing needs. At a time when global marine biodiversity data is becoming a sought-after asset, OBIS must adopt an inclusive, community-based, future-facing posture to remain a keystone in intersecting marine biodiversity data and tools with international marine conservation efforts.</p>]]></content><author><name>OBIS</name></author><category term="OBIS Executive Committee" /><category term="Nodes Coordination Group" /><category term="Data Coordination Group" /><category term="Product Coordination Group" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Ocean Biodiversity Information System (OBIS) Executive Committee meeting took place at the InnovOcean Campus in Oostende, Belgium, from 14 to 16 October 2024\. The meeting aimed to set OBIS's strategic course for 2025 and establish a visionary document to set long-term goals and foster synergies with other IODE activities. In this article, we outline the three essential takeaways from the meeting.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/EC6-thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/EC6-thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">PacMAN Fiji achieves “Marine Invasive Species Monitoring-Ready” status as project is completed</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/11/21/pacman-conclusion-news.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PacMAN Fiji achieves “Marine Invasive Species Monitoring-Ready” status as project is completed" /><published>2024-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/11/21/pacman-conclusion-news</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/11/21/pacman-conclusion-news.html"><![CDATA[<p>Marine invasive species threaten biodiversity, ecosystems, and the livelihoods of Small Island Developing States (SIDS) like Fiji. These organisms disrupt fragile marine ecosystems, endanger native species, and undermine the blue economy. PacMAN was designed to combat these challenges by equipping Fiji with state-of-the-art tools, robust protocols, and expert training to enable rapid detection and effective management.</p>

<div class="post-quote">
"Invasive species are like wildfires—you want to stop them before they spread out of control. Thanks to support from OBIS, Fiji now has the tools to monitor and detect marine invasive species early." 
    <div class="post-quote-author">Ward Appeltans, OBIS Programme Manager</div>
</div>

<p>The project also aligns with <a href="https://www.cbd.int/gbf/targets/6"><strong>Target 6</strong></a> <strong>of the Kunming-Montreal Global Biodiversity Framework</strong>, adopted under the Convention on Biological Diversity, which calls for reducing the introduction and establishment of invasive alien species, particularly in vulnerable ecosystems. By developing local capacity, fostering cross-sector collaboration, and implementing advanced monitoring systems, PacMAN provides a practical model for achieving this global biodiversity target.</p>

<p><strong>Key Achievements of PacMAN:</strong></p>

<p>- <strong>Innovative Monitoring Protocols</strong>: Developed and tested a comprehensive plan for systematic data collection on invasive species, ensuring local relevance.</p>

<p>- <strong>Cutting-Edge Molecular Techniques</strong>: Conducted Fiji’s first-ever environmental DNA (eDNA) training, equipping local scientists and technicians with skills in eDNA analysis and qPCR assays for early detection of high-risk species.</p>

<p>- <strong>Scientific Insights</strong>: Analysed 188 samples using metabarcoding, identifying <a href="https://portal.pacman.obis.org/?area=&amp;confidence=&amp;risk_level=high">four high-risk invasive species</a> and assessed 1000s of potential invasive species.</p>

<p>- <strong>Technological Advancements</strong>: Developed the PacMAN <a href="https://github.com/iobis/PacMAN-pipeline">bioinformatics pipeline</a> aligned with global biodiversity data standards and the <a href="https://portal.pacman.obis.org">PacMAN decision support too</a>l integrated into the Ocean Biodiversity Information System (OBIS) for rapid invasive species alerts.</p>

<p>- <strong>Regional Leadership</strong>: Risk-assessed thousands of species to inform proactive management strategies, positioning Fiji as a leader in marine biosecurity efforts.</p>

<p>eDNA technology, which detects genetic material left behind by organisms in the environment, emerged as a game-changing tool in this project. Its sensitivity, scalability, and cost-effectiveness make it an ideal solution for addressing biosecurity challenges in Fiji and across the Pacific region.</p>

<p><strong>Collaboration for Success</strong></p>

<p>PacMAN’s achievements was made possible through the collaboration of numerous stakeholders, including Fiji’s Ministry of Environment, the Ministry of Fisheries, the Biosecurity Authority, the Maritime Safety Authority, the Fiji Ports Corporation, and regional partners such as SPREP and SPC. International expertise from institutions like Deakin University, the University of the South Pacific, and the OBIS team also played a pivotal role in the project’s success.</p>

<p>As the project transitions to local leadership, UNESCO’s Intergovernmental Oceanographic Commission (IOC) remains committed to supporting Fiji and the wider Pacific region in scaling up marine biosecurity efforts. By building on PacMAN’s foundations, Fiji is poised to lead regional initiatives to protect marine ecosystems and sustain livelihoods dependent on the ocean.</p>

<p><strong>A Step Toward Global Goals</strong></p>

<p>The successful implementation of PacMAN protects Fiji’s marine biodiversity. It contributes to the global effort to address the threats of invasive species under Target 6 of the Kunming-Montreal Global Biodiversity Framework. This success underscores the importance of local capacity building and innovative science in achieving meaningful progress toward biodiversity conservation goals.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4DhaCKzd2IU?si=AEnuB6iMuSuuBXt_" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>Looking Ahead</strong></p>

<p>The conclusion of PacMAN marks a significant milestone, but the fight against marine invasive species continues. With strengthened capacity, advanced tools, and a collaborative framework, Fiji is well-equipped to safeguard its marine environments and inspire similar efforts across the Pacific.          	Together, we can protect the ocean and the communities it sustains.</p>

<p>The 4 year PacMAN project was funded by the Flanders Government through the UNESCO-Flanders Trust Fund for Science (FUST).
For further details, visit <a href="https://portal.pacman.obis.org/about">https://portal.pacman.obis.org/about</a> or contact pacman@obis.org.</p>]]></content><author><name>OBIS</name></author><category term="PacMAN" /><category term="Capacity building" /><category term="eDNA" /><category term="marine invasive species" /><category term="Policy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Suva, Fiji, 20 November 2024 – The Pacific Islands Marine Bioinvasions Alert Network (PacMAN) has concluded with resounding success, positioning Fiji as the first island nation recognised by UNESCO as "marine invasive species monitoring ready." Supported by the Flanders Government (Kingdom of Belgium), the four-year IOC-UNESCO project has significantly strengthened Fiji's ability to address the growing challenge of marine invasive species.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/PacMAN-completion-thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/PacMAN-completion-thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">New OTGA/OBIS course in Spanish: Fundamentos para la publicación de datos de biodiversidad marina en OBIS</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/10/28/otga-spanish-course.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New OTGA/OBIS course in Spanish: Fundamentos para la publicación de datos de biodiversidad marina en OBIS" /><published>2024-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/10/28/otga-spanish-course</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/10/28/otga-spanish-course.html"><![CDATA[<p>OBIS Colombia, OBIS Caribe, and ESP-OBIS have joined together to launch a self-paced course in Spanish on the Ocean Teacher Global Academy (OTGA) platform. This course, “Fundamentos para la publicación de datos de biodiversidad marina en OBIS”, is tailored for those who want to learn how to publish data through the OBIS, particularly those in Latin America. The course, spanning five modules, covers OBIS data standards, data table formats and structures, basic quality control, data publication, and data visualization tools. For more details on the course, click <a href="https://oceanexpert.org/event/4571">here</a>.</p>

<p>The OBIS Secretariat thanks the following instructors for leading this effort:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Erika Montoya-Cadavid (OBIS Colombia)</li>
  <li>Martha Vides Casado (OBIS Colombia)</li>
  <li>Carolina Peralta Brichtova (OBIS Caribe)</li>
  <li>Jeannette Pérez (OBIS Caribe)</li>
  <li>Joxmer Scott-Frías (OBIS Caribe)</li>
  <li>Pamela Hidalgo Díaz (ESP-OBIS)</li>
  <li>Pedro Aros-Mardones (ESP-OBIS)</li>
  <li>Braulio Fernández (ESP OBIS) - <a href="https://oceanexpert.org/event/3983">OBIS certified</a></li>
  <li>Ignacio Ibáñez Lara (ESP-OBIS) - <a href="https://oceanexpert.org/event/3983">OBIS certified</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The course is freely accessible through the OTGA platform: https://classroom.oceanteacher.org/course/view.php?id=948 by logging in with an OceanExpert account and using the enrollment key INVEMAR**OBIS2024. Course completion will take approximately 20 hours. This course is also based on the previously released English OBIS/OTGA course, <a href="https://oceanexpert.org/event/3983">Contributing and publishing datasets to OBIS</a>.</p>

<p>For more information please contact:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="mailto:ioc.training@unesco.org">ioc.training@unesco.org</a> (OTGA Coordinator)</li>
  <li><a href="mailto:erika.montoya@invemar.org.co">erika.montoya@invemar.org.co</a> (INVEMAR)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>OBIS secretariat</name></author><category term="OBIS" /><category term="OTGA" /><category term="training" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[OBIS Colombia, OBIS Caribe, and ESP-OBIS have launched a self-paced course in Spanish on OTGA, covering OBIS data standards, quality control, and publishing. Available from 4 Oct, 2024 to 30 Jan, 2025.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/new-spanish-course-thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/new-spanish-course-thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">OBIS eDNA services, expertise and data publication</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/10/22/obis-edna.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OBIS eDNA services, expertise and data publication" /><published>2024-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/10/22/obis-edna</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/10/22/obis-edna.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="obis-edna-services-expertise-and-data-publication">OBIS eDNA services, expertise and data publication</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="##Overview">Introduction to eDNA and OBIS</a></li>
  <li><a href="##Publishing-eDNA-data-to-OBIS">Publishing eDNA data to OBIS</a></li>
  <li><a href="##Accessing-eDNA-data-from-OBIS">Accessing eDNA data from OBIS</a></li>
  <li><a href="#edna-services-and-resources-developed-by-obis">eDNA services and resources developed by OBIS</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#citizen-science-edna-sampling-protocols">Citizen Science eDNA Sampling Protocols</a></li>
      <li><a href="#bioinformatics-pipeline--from-raw-sequences-to-species-annotated-data-in-obis">Bioinformatics pipeline : from raw sequences to species-annotated data in OBIS</a></li>
      <li><a href="#analytical-tools">Analytical tools</a></li>
      <li><a href="#capacity-building-and-training">Capacity building and training</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#obis-projects-developing-edna-research-tools-and-standards">OBIS projects developing eDNA research, tools and standards</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>
<h3 id="introduction-to-edna">Introduction to eDNA</h3>
<p>Environmental DNA, or eDNA, refers to the genetic material that can be extracted from an environmental sample such as (sea)water, sediment, soil, or even air. This genetic material can be analysed with a set of molecular tools to infer information about the organisms living in the sampled environment. This DNA was shed as waste, mucus, or cells and the analyses vary from presence/absence detection with taxon-specific genetic markers, to the characterization of whole communities or even multi-species assemblages with broad-use markers. Sampling and analysing environmental DNA allows us to study the diversity of oceanographic life from its smallest fraction invisible to the naked eye to its largest inhabitants that are nonetheless challenging to survey, and all the organisms that fall in between.</p>

<p>The cost effective, ethical nature of eDNA sampling has the potential to revolutionise our knowledge about ecosystems and species diversity, and unlock new insights for biodiversity studies, environmental monitoring, as well as provide reliable data to support decision-making. The potential for standardisation with well-documented protocols and supporting metadata represent an important step in generating and sharing biodiversity data that is globally accessible, comparable and reusable.</p>

<h3 id="summary-of-obis-edna-services">Summary of OBIS eDNA services</h3>
<p>OBIS, the Ocean Biodiversity Information System, is actively engaged in eDNA research and the eDNA research community. Through its many projects, OBIS develops tools for the bioinformatic processing and analysis of eDNA data, works on the development of metadata standards, and can provide services to support partners in field sampling and lab work, and in making eDNA data findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable (FAIR).</p>

<p>As a data publication platform, OBIS provides rigorous quality control and can publish occurrence data derived from quantitative (qPCR/ddPCR) or community-level (metabarcoding) eDNA approaches following community-approved data standards. This data can in turn be queried and accessed from OBIS to increase the reach and application of eDNA-based biodiversity data. The associated metadata not only provides the essential sampling information (longitude &amp; latitude coordinates, depth, …) but allows publishers to link critical information on the environment sampled, the different protocols and methods used across the workflow (target gene, primer sequences, clustering or denoising approach, reference database used, …), the DOI of the published study the data comes from, as well as link back to the original sequence data deposited in INSDC databases (e.g. EMBL-EBI’s ENA or NCBI’s SRA).</p>

<h2 id="publishing-edna-data-to-obis">Publishing eDNA data to OBIS</h2>

<p>The guidebook on <a href="https://docs.gbif.org/publishing-dna-derived-data/en/" target="_blank">Publishing DNA-derived data through biodiversity data platforms</a>, co-authored by OBIS and GBIF, provides a comprehensive view of why, where and how to publish DNA-derived biodiversity data. 
The <a href="https://manual.obis.org" target="_blank">OBIS manual</a> further provides all the information needed to publish biodiversity data to OBIS, with a section dedicated to <a href="https://manual.obis.org/dna_data.html" target="_blank">publishing DNA-derived data</a>.</p>

<p>The data published to OBIS follows the Darwin Core community data format, ensuring the data is interoperable across many databases, searchable, accessible and machine-readable. A detailed explanation of the terms are readily available in the <a href="https://docs.gbif.org/publishing-dna-derived-data/en/#data-mapping">Guidelines Document - 2.2 Data Mapping</a> and the dedicated <a href="https://rs.gbif.org/extension/gbif/1.0/dna_derived_data_2022-02-23.xml">DwC dnaderivdedata extension</a> page. The OBIS resources page hosts a tool for <a href="https://resources.obis.org/find-your-dwc/">finding the right DwC format</a>. In short, DNA-derived data is published to OBIS as an Occurrence core dataset supplemented with the DNA derived data extension. The occurrence table captures information such as the occurrence id, sampling date, location, time, ASV, read abundance, taxonomic assignment and the taxon’s corresponding WoRMS ID. The dnaderiveddata table in turns captures DNA-specific information such as the target gene, primers used, sequencing platform, bioinformatic parameters and the ASV sequence. It again contains the occurrence id to link the data to the occurrence table.</p>

<p>A series of video tutorials are available on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@oceanbiodiversityinformati6931">OBIS Youtube Channel</a> to help you prepare and publish your datasets. These include the series <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLlgUwSvpCFS4TS7ZN0fhByj_3EBZ5lXbF">How To Use &amp; Publish data with OBIS</a> which explains how to format your datasets to follow DwC criteria. OBIS also organised a webinar on genetic data, with an introduction to how OBIS is incorporating data, how genetic data can be accessed and a use case from the first eDNA dataset provided by OBIS-USA. The recording of the webinar can be watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KKh_Hd8zybs">here</a>.</p>

<p>Finally, OBIS has an example eDNA metabarcoding dataset with scripts for data formatting available on the <a href="https://github.com/iobis/dataset-edna">OBIS github page</a>.</p>

<h3 id="obis-vs-gbif-marine-specific-guidelines-tailored-for-obis">OBIS vs GBIF: marine-specific guidelines tailored for OBIS</h3>

<p>OBIS - the <a href="https://obis.org/">Ocean Biodiversity Information System</a> — and GBIF — the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a> are both global biodiversity data sharing platforms and have a <a href="https://doi.org/10.35035/doc-kcqs-5h52">joint strategy</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.35035/doc-e52v-5875">action plan</a> to ensure the cross-platform flows and services of high-quality data about marine and coastal biodiversity. Both platforms use the same guidelines and Darwin Core community data format, and the same <a href="https://manual.obis.org/ipt">Integrated Publishing Toolkit (IPT)</a> to publish and register datasets. When publishing a dataset through either OBIS or GBIF nodes, selecting the option to register the data to GBIF or OBIS ensures that the data flows from one platform to the next.</p>

<p>OBIS is focused on the marine realm and marine taxa, whereas GBIF publishes data across both terrestrial and marine realms. With the focus on marine datasets, stringent quality controls on the data published to OBIS increase the reliability of the data and lead to small differences in what information is required for publishing in OBIS as opposed to GBIF. The two main differences consider the taxonomic backbone used and the geographic coordinates data checks:</p>
<ul>
  <li>To ensure consistent taxonomic nomenclature OBIS uses the <a href="https://www.marinespecies.org/">World Register of Marine Species (WoRMS)</a> as the only taxonomic backbone. This is the case also for occurrences derived from genetic data; a scientific name linked to a scientific name ID from the WoRMS database is highly recommended information for publishing. […] Fully unclassified sequences are recommended to be classified as “incertae sedis”, with the WoRMS <em>scientificNameID urn:lsid:marinespecies.org:taxname:12</em>.</li>
  <li>Another required field in OBIS data submissions are geographic coordinates. OBIS performs additional quality checks related to marine data; e.g. that coordinates for strictly marine species are not on land, and that the depth value reported is in a reasonable range.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="accessing-edna-data-from-obis">Accessing eDNA data from OBIS</h2>

<p>Data in general, and DNA-derived data specifically, can be queried and downloaded from OBIS through the online mapper or the R package robis. This is also covered in the OBIS manual under <a href="https://manual.obis.org/dna_data.html#how-to-find-genetic-data-in-obis">“How to find genetic data in OBIS”</a>.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Using the mapper</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>The <a href="https://mapper.obis.org">mapper tool</a> allows you to query biodiversity data on OBIS by searching for data using specific criteria such as scientific name or geographic area. 
eDNA-based biodiversity data can also specifically be searched for by specifying the option for <a href="https://mapper.obis.org/?hasextensions=DNADerivedData#">DNAderiveddata</a> under the Extensions tab. As of the day of publishing this article, the resulting data layer holds <strong>19,815,140 records</strong> of <strong>5,226 species</strong> and <strong>8,694 taxa</strong> across 51 datasets.</p>

<p>Once this layer is added, the data can be downloaded either all together as Darwin Core Archive dataset, or you can access each published dataset separately and download the original Darwin Core formatted files. If the dataset originates from a published study, the doi of that paper is provided to link to all the necessary information.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Data access tools (R, API)</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Genetic data can also be accessed from OBIS using the R package <a href="https://github.com/iobis/robis">robis</a>. Instructions for using the robis package to access DNA derived data can be found in the <a href="https://manual.obis.org/access.html#r-package">OBIS manual</a> and the dedicated <a href="https://iobis.github.io/notebook-dnaderiveddata/">vignette</a>.</p>

<p>Both the mapper and the R package are based on the <a href="https://api.obis.org/">OBIS API</a>, which can also be used to find and download data. When <a href="https://manual.obis.org/access.html#api">using the API</a> directly, you can filter the Occurrence records by specifying the extension DNADerivedData. You can further search through this e.g. by scientific name, date, depth, coordinates, or country.</p>

<h3 id="examples-of-edna-datasets-hosted-on-obis">Examples of eDNA datasets hosted on OBIS</h3>

<p>There are currently 51 eDNA datasets publicly available on OBIS, amounting to 19,815,140 records of 5,226 species and 8,694 taxa.</p>

<p>A few examples:</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://obis.org/dataset/dbb57c74-c34c-4502-b1d0-15324a7fabc4">Environmental DNA reveals tropical shark diversity in contrasting levels of anthropogenic impact.</a> 
This dataset has appeared in 3,643 downloads in 2024, with a total of 1,053,527 records.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Confirmation of pygmy sperm whale, Kogia breviceps from Palk Bay, India through Cytochrome Oxidase1 (COI) sequence.   https://obis.org/dataset/f6db2e52-e89d-4e7b-950d-6001e54424c9</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ecosystem biomonitoring with eDNA: Metabarcoding across the tree of life in a tropical marine environment. Coral Bay, Ningaloo Reef, Western Australia (2015)
https://obis.org/dataset/d71b6687-810e-4234-ae31-386017b5b08a</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Marine zooplankton community structure through environmental DNA metabarcoding in the Florida Keys, collected by the South Florida Program (NOAA/AOML) and the Marine Biodiversity Observation Network (MBON)
https://obis.org/dataset/b41e10e2-5717-4bb3-b06a-7840a62aebcc</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="edna-services-and-resources-developed-by-obis">eDNA services and resources developed by OBIS</h2>

<p>A set of different tools and services were developed within the different eDNA projects led or supported by OBIS. These cover the different steps across an eDNA workflow, ranging from developing sampling protocols for citizen science, to developing bioinformatics pipelines to process raw eDNA sequences and enable the export of eDNA-derived biodiversity data ready to be uploaded to OBIS and accessed by users worldwide.</p>

<p>In addition to these services already developed, OBIS can guide partners across these steps in designing and carrying out eDNA studies as well as develop new tools depending on the project’s need.</p>

<h3 id="citizen-science-edna-sampling-protocols">Citizen Science eDNA Sampling Protocols</h3>

<p>As part of the <a href="https://www.unesco.org/en/edna-expeditions">eDNA expeditions</a> project, the OBIS team collaboratively developed citizen science protocols for sampling eDNA. An instruction video, sampling booklets detailing the protocol in six languages and sample information sheets and infographics can be downloaded under the <a href="https://www.unesco.org/en/edna-training-materials?hub=66910">eDNA expeditions
Training Materials</a>.</p>

<h3 id="bioinformatics-pipeline--from-raw-sequences-to-species-annotated-data-in-obis">Bioinformatics pipeline : from raw sequences to species-annotated data in OBIS</h3>

<p>OBIS developed a bioinformatics pipeline for processing raw metabarcoding sequences under the <a href="https://pacman.obis.org">PacMAN project</a>. Broadly speaking, it creates a framework that receives raw sequence data from eDNA samples, cleans, aligns, classifies sequences, and finally outputs a DwC-compatible table. To note, the pipeline automatically searches for aphia-IDs from WoRMS to include in the DWC-compatible tables. In addition the output also contains a phyloseq object, which is compatible with the commonly used phyloseq R package for sequence data analysis. The pipeline is under active development. More details about the PacMAN pipeline can be found on its associated <a href="https://github.com/iobis/PacMAN-pipeline">GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<h3 id="analytical-tools">Analytical tools</h3>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>robis <br />
  <a href="https://manual.obis.org/access.html#r-package">robis</a> is OBIS’ flagship R package and a client for the OBIS API. It includes functions for data access, as well as a few helper functions for visualising occurrence data and extracting nested MeasurementOrFact or DNADerivedData records.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>obistools: Tools for data enhancement and quality control.<br />
  <a href="https://iobis.github.io/obistools/">obistools</a> is an R package developed by OBIS collating a set of functions to check and map Darwin Core fields from a dataset and plot datapoints on a map.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sequence Search Tool (in development) <br />
A prototype <a href="https://sequence.obis.org/">Sequence Search tool</a> is in development that allows you to search for sequences or related sequences in OBIS. More info can be found in the <a href="https://manual.obis.org/dna_data.html#how-to-find-genetic-data-in-obis">OBIS manual</a>.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="capacity-building-and-training">Capacity building and training</h3>

<p>OBIS provides training on eDNA sampling and analysis methods. These can e.g. be tailored towards scientists, practitioners, site managers or policy makers.</p>

<p>A first training course was organised in Fiji in 2023 under the PacMAN project. The focus was on eDNA sampling, DNA extraction, qPCR for the detection of invasive species, and bioinformatic processing of metabarcoding data. All information and necessary links can be found on the PacMAN project website under the <a href="https://pacman.obis.org/2023/04/21/pacman-scientific-training-course-online/">“Marine Invasive Species Early Detection: Utilising Molecular Tools” training course page</a>.</p>

<h2 id="obis-projects-developing-edna-research-tools-and-standards">OBIS projects developing eDNA research, tools and standards</h2>
<p>OBIS is currently leading two large-scale research and surveillance projects, engaging citizens globally to survey the biodiversity across 25 marine UNESCO World Heritage sites (eDNA expeditions) and developing information networks for the surveillance of marine invasive species in the Pacific (PacMANn). OBIS also participates in two Horizon Europe projects reviewing bioinformatic workflows (MARCO-BOLO), and rethinking the eDNA data publishing infrastructure and metadata standards (eDNAqua-Plan).</p>

<p><img alt="eDNAexpeditions" src="/images/ednaexpeditions_kids.jpg" width="50%" /></p>

<p>https://www.unesco.org/en/edna-expeditions</p>

<p><img alt="pacman-logo" src="/images/pacman_logo.png" width="50%" /></p>

<p>https://pacman.obis.org/</p>

<p><img alt="ednaquaplan-logo" src="/images/ednaquaplan_logo.png" width="50%" /></p>

<p>https://ednaquaplan.com/</p>

<p><img alt="marcobolo-logo" src="/images/marcobolo_logo.png" width="50%" /></p>

<p>https://marcobolo-project.eu/</p>]]></content><author><name>Emilie Boulanger, Saara Suominen</name></author><category term="OBIS" /><category term="eDNA" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[OBIS is actively engaged in eDNA research and the eDNA research community. Through its many projects, OBIS develops monitoring studies as well as tools for the bioinformatic processing and analysis of eDNA data, and works on the development of community-approved metadata standards. As a data publication platform, OBIS enables research teams, authors, and monitoring projects to publish occurrence data derived from quantitative (qPCR/ddPCR) or community-level (metabarcoding) eDNA approaches to make ocean biodiversity data globally accessible.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/obis_edna_thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/obis_edna_thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Hack for a Livable Planet: join OBIS at the World Bank-led hackathon to answer biodiversity issues using available data</title><link href="https://obis.org/2024/10/22/wb-hackathon-obis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hack for a Livable Planet: join OBIS at the World Bank-led hackathon to answer biodiversity issues using available data" /><published>2024-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://obis.org/2024/10/22/wb-hackathon-obis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://obis.org/2024/10/22/wb-hackathon-obis.html"><![CDATA[<p>Scientific organizations worldwide have collected local and global biodiversity data, sometimes for several decades. “We have historical datasets that date back to 1900,” explains Ward Appeltans, OBIS Programme Manager. “This long-term data is crucial for understanding change patterns and rates of ocean biodiversity loss.” Globally, hundreds of organizations are collecting, treating, storing, and making <a href="https://spatialagent.org/BiodiversityHackathon/resources.html" target="_blank">boundless quantities</a> of biodiversity data available to everyone. Traditionally, scientists, researchers, conservationists, decision-makers, and industry professionals have been the biggest consumers of this stored data, utilizing it to better understand the Earth’s systems, inform, and make evidence-based decisions. With guidance, incentives, and collaborative processes, broader groups, such as citizens, could also utilize this publicly available data to highlight biodiversity issues, bring in new perspectives, and improve awareness from local to global levels.</p>

<p>Organized by the World Bank Group and supported by its evolving Livable Planet Observatory, “Hack for a Livable Planet” is a virtual hackathon encouraging diverse teams of all ages, genders, expertise, and backgrounds to explore and build new outcomes for publicly available biodiversity data. The event launched on 15 October 2024 and will run until mid-December 2024, with two phases of competition. The first phase will end on 11 November 2024. Participants can find <a href="https://spatialagent.org/BiodiversityHackathon/faq.html" target="_blank">more details</a> on the hackathon’s FAQ page.</p>

<p>The hackathon is built around three main windows. “E-Packaging” aims at fostering powerful data-based narratives expressed through browser-based, dynamic digital formats such as storymaps, dashboards, webapps, infographics, interactive visualizations or audio &amp; video experiences. “Policy Memo” seeks to channel biodiversity data into digestible, topic-focused memos advocating for policy change and aiming at real-world implementation. “Coding” is focused on developing free, open-source tools for analyzing public-domain data to get new insights on some relevant aspects of biodiversity, habitats, or ecosystems.</p>

<h2 id="dedicated-hands-on-resources-from-obis"><strong>Dedicated hands-on resources from OBIS</strong></h2>

<p>Along with 11 other significant global scientific organizations, OBIS, a proud event partner, has developed specific tools to help the hackathon participants make the most of its 135 million ocean species occurrence records! Participants can get an overview of these resources in our dedicated <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=D-qawZl7Q2g" target="_blank">video</a> and below.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/iobis/hackathon" target="_blank"><strong>OBIS GitHub hackathon portal</strong></a><br />
In this portal, participants can find, for example, R code for retrieving and working with data subsets and dedicated packages for Python and R. Participants can also download a complete export of the OBIS database to your computer.</p>

<p><strong>OBIS speciesgrids</strong><br />
We have developed the <a href="https://github.com/iobis/speciesgrids" target="_blank">“speciesgrids”</a>, a new dataset combining all OBIS and GBIF marine records in a gridded format. Using Uber’s H3 index system, speciesgrids allow for lightning-fast spatial queries and are delivered in a lightweight, user-friendly format—perfect for this hackathon!</p>

<p><strong>R &amp; Python notebooks</strong><br />
Our team has prepared a collection of <a href="https://github.com/iobis/hackathon/tree/master/notebooks" target="_blank">R and Python notebooks</a> to help participants access, clean, manipulate, and visualize biodiversity data effortlessly. Participants can download the notebooks or open them directly in <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/github/iobis/hackathon" target="_blank">Google Colab</a>, which offers a seamless online Jupyter environment for running your code.</p>

<p><strong>Binder</strong><br />
Participants can also use Binder, which supports JupyterHub and RStudio and allows executing our notebooks in the cloud.</p>

<p><strong>It’s in the manual!</strong><br />
We have a <a href="https://manual.obis.org/" target="_blank">comprehensive manual</a> where participants who want to dive deeper into OBIS will find detailed guidance on accessing and using our data, step-by-step tutorials, and tips to enhance research. This manual was designed for beginners and experts alike!</p>

<p><strong>We have more in stock!</strong><br />
The OBIS website is rich with additional resources that will be helpful to participants during this hackathon: the <a href="https://github.com/iobis/hackathon/tree/master/notebooks?tab=readme-ov-file#other-resources" target="_blank">“Other Resources”</a> section includes links and video guides to boost the participants’ data efficiency!</p>

<p>We can’t wait to see what is created with the OBIS data at the “Hack for a Livable Planet” hackathon!</p>

<p>More info https://spatialagent.org/BiodiversityHackathon/faq.html</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=D-qawZl7Q2g"><img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/D-qawZl7Q2g/0.jpg" alt="video" /></a></p>]]></content><author><name>OBIS secretariat</name></author><category term="OBIS" /><category term="hackathon" /><category term="resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Biodiversity loss is one of the three main global threats to life on Earth, and if not addressed, could lead to a massive ecosystem collapse. Finding implementable solutions to protect biodiversity is critical for sustaining life on Earth and mitigating the ongoing environmental crises. OBIS is teaming up with the World Bank in a hackathon where citizens of all ages, researchers, community leaders, educators, activists, and elders team up to transform troves of publicly available biodiversity data repositories into actionable tools for education, policymaking and analysis. The great news? You can take part, too!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://obis.org/images/wb_hackathon_thumb.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://obis.org/images/wb_hackathon_thumb.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>